Marilynn Gelfman Karp Collection of Ephemera PR 279
New-York Historical Society
Marilynn Gelfman Karp Collection of Ephemera
1842-1985
1870-1955
New-York Historical Society
PR 279
6.25 Linear feet
Ephemera materials spanning the late 19th to mid 20th centuries, including trade cards, blotters, cigarette silks, product and dry good labels, greeting cards, postcards, and hairnet packages, among others.
Provenance
Gift of Marilynn Gelfman Karp, 2009
Access
The collection is open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been photocopied or microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format; microfilm can be made available through Interlibrary Loan.
Permission to reproduce or quote in publication
Application to use images from this collection for publication should be made in writing to the Department of Rights and Reproductions, The New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, New York, NY 10024. Permission to reproduce or quote text from this collection in a publication must be requested from and granted in writing by the Library Director, The New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, New York, NY 10024.
Biographical Notes
Marilynn Gelfman Karp:
Marilynn Gelfman Karp was born in the Bronx, New York, in 1939. Her penchant for collecting began early in childhood, with the careful culling of objects from her everyday life, including things that came in the family mail (greeting cards, attractive postcards, circulars), from family life (milk bottle lids, cigar bands, cigar boxes, campaign buttons, advertising giveaways), things that were found in the street (odd bits of metal, rocks, phenomena with power), gleaned from the grocery store (wooden cheese boxes, fruit crate labels), purchased from or found around the local candy store (bubblegum cards, Dixie lids, soda bottle tops), or from Woolworth's (Jack O'Lanterns, marbles, dexterity games, skate keys), or things from the luncheonette (sugar packets, soda fountain cut-outs). Relatives occasionally gave her relevant objects (foreign coins from service in World War II, pipe tobacco tins, cocktail mixers, figural matches, license plate key chain tags). As she grew up, Karp spent her allowance on things that were important to her (Indian bubblegum cards, trading cards, Cracker Jacks for the prizes, cockamamies, radio premium rings and decoders) and packaging that was compelling (hairnet envelopes, decals).
A deep fascination and perceptive appreciation for the beauty and meaning in everyday objects has characterized her collecting ever since. Karp's passion for collecting is equally shared with her husband, contemporary art dealer Ivan C. Karp, who has been an integral appreciator and inspiration for Karp in the formation of her over 200 well-managed and archivally kept collections of ephemera. Stopping at every flea market, antique show, antique shop, collectibles show, and yard sale that looks interesting to her, she describes these venues as having one thing in common: "they are places of unconditional seeking and possessing. Each object has a story to tell, somewhat fleshing out a time."
Collecting on instinct, each object that Karp has chosen to own is recognized by her as "a material incident in which time and place coalesce in a palpably pungent way." Scanning the past, she considers the objects she encounters in their "much diminished range from when they were new," trying to prevent the "irreversible elimination" of what she feels are "significant and resounding things that inform us about the times in which they were made."
Karp's collecting activities have been additionally informed by her educational background and professional accomplishments in the visual arts. Receiving both a B.F.A. in Studio Art (1958) and an M.A. in Art History (1962) from Hunter College, she then went on to earn a Ph.D. in Physics and Aesthetics from New York University (1965), where she served as a Professor of Art at NYU's Steinhardt School, Department of Art and Art Professions for 42 years. Initially teaching basic 3D design and art history in Western culture, Karp's teaching activities later gravitated toward American art and architecture in the context of cultural history. In this capacity, she was actively involved with M.A. and M.F.A. graduating exhibition classes, and as an advisor, reader, and chair, for many doctoral dissertation committees in art, critical studies, and material culture.
During her years as a professor at NYU, Karp made important and far-reaching contributions to the study of material culture within the University's curriculum, designing and instituting the country's first Master's degree in Visual Arts Administration and Collecting, an M.A. Program in Folk Art (NYU in collaboration with the American Folk Art Museum, NY) and an M.A. program in Costume Studies (NYU in collaboration with the Metropolitan Museum of Art's Costume Institute).
Beyond her successful career in academia, Karp is a professional sculptor of international achievement, and is an American Academy of Arts and Letters Sculptor's Award recipient. Her collecting interests have helped to shape her creative work, which utilizes a variety of mixed media and found objects. Additionally, she has served as a Trustee and Board Member for a number of organizations devoted to historic preservation and art in public spaces, including the Preservation League of New York State, The Public Art Fund, and the Anonymous Arts Recovery Society.
In 2006, Karp chronicled her adventures in collecting with the publication In Flagrante Collecto, published by Harry N. Abrams, which celebrates the odd, arcane, quotidian collectible, as both an object of desire and of cultural anthropology. With the donation of this collection of ephemera to the New-York Historical Society, it is her belief and hope that the public-at-large will be afforded an important brush with material culture, and that museums in general will continue to preserve and serve up these objects to future audiences who will see them with the perspective and clarity that distance affords.
Ivan Karp and OK Harris:
Ivan Karp was an art dealer, author, and American gallerist. Karp was considerably involved in the Photo Realist movement in 1969. He was co-director at the Leo Castelli Gallery between 1959 – 1969, during which time he was instrumental in launching the careers of many renowned pop artists, most notably Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Robert Rauschenberg, Tom Wesselmann and John Chamberlain. In 1969 Karp decided to launch his own gallery, OK Harris, which was located on 465 West Broadway and survived from 1969 until June 2014. The establishment of OK Harris as the first gallery on West Broadway made a significant contribution to the development of the SoHo area's fine arts character. OK Harris exhibited contemporary art and photography, and on occasion mounted shows of antiques and collectibles. The gallery's aim was to show significant artwork without prejudice as to the style or materials employed, the sole criteria was innovation of concept and maturity of technique. Karp died on June 28, 2012 at the age of 86, in New York. OK Harris closed its doors in June 2014.
Scope and Content Notes
The Marilynn Gelfman Karp Collection of Ephemera consists of approximately 6.25 linear feet of materials spanning the late 19th to mid 20th centuries. The materials represent an eclectic variety of ephemera in various formats (mostly paper), of once ubiquitous items that were expected to have short-term uses in their time, including trade cards, blotters, cigarette silks, product and dry good labels, greeting cards, postcards, and hairnet packages, among others.
Related Materials
Marilynn Gelfman Karp has also donated additional ephemara objects that are cataloged and housed separately within the New-York Historical Society's Museum collection.
The Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera ca. 1700-present PR 031
Collection of mainly 19th and 20th century advertising ephemera. Formats in the collection include American trade cards, lottery tickets, handbills, labels, broadsides, calendars, billheads, price lists, advertising fans, and other materials of history and popular culture. Media range from rough woodcuts to chromolithographs.
Arrangement
The 17 series and corresponding subseries reflect Karp's own organization of the collection by format, and in some cases by subject.
Missing Title
Series I. Greeting Cards, circa 1925-1945
Series II. Postcards, circa 1906-1955
Series III. Trade Cards, circa 1875-1915
Series IV. Blotters, circa 1890-1955
Series V. Cigarette Silks, circa 1900-1915
Series VI. Needle Books, circa 1870-1955
Series VII. Labels (paper and tin), circa 1875-1955
Series VIII. Pictorial Glassine Snack Bags, circa 1935-1955
Series IX. Hairnets in Packaging, circa 1920s-1967
Series X. Decals, circa 1930-1955
Series XI. World War II Ephemera (various formats), circa 1942-1945
Series XII. Miscellaneous Paper Items, undated
Series XIII. Annual Linoleum Pattern Books, 1921-1952
Series XIV. Hairdressing Magazines, 1938-1950
Series XV. Sheet Music, 1842-1948
Series XVI. Photography, circa 1880s-1945
Series XVII. Prints and Drawings, 1930
References
Burns, S. B. (1990). Sleeping beauty: Memorial photography in America. Altadena, CA: Twelvetree Press.
Collecting antique tins. (n.d.). In Collectible Collectibles. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://www.collectablecollectables.com/articles.asp
Editorial chit-chat: A new style of net [Electronic version]. (1863, July). Peterson's Magazine, 44(1).
Gartrell, E. (n.d.). More about advertising ephemera and the advertising ephemera collection. In Emergence of Advertising in America: 1850-1920. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://library.duke.edu/digitalcollections/eaa/guide/ephemera/
Hagley Museum and Library. (n.d.). Leonard W. Walton printing and packaging collection. In Hagley Museum and Library. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://www.hagley.lib.de.us/library/collections/manuscripts/findingaids/Walton_ACC2430.pdf
Heyman, T. T. (1998). Posters American style. New York: National Museum of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.
"Hit Kit" spells post-war music [Electronic version]. (1944, February 19). The Billboard, 13, 17.
Karp, M. G. (2006). In flagrante collecto: Caught in the act of collecting. New York: Abrams.
Laughing Elephant. (n.d.). Luggage Labels. In The Savvy Traveller. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://www.thesavvytraveller.com/tools/laughing_elephant/1home.htm
Lester, K., & Oerke, B. V. (2004). Accessories of dress: An illustrated encyclopedia. Mineola, NY: Dover Publications. (Original work published 1940)
New York State Library. (n.d.). Wish you were here: The story of the golden age of picture postcards in the United States. In New York State Education Department. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://www.nysl.nysed.gov/msscfa/qc16510ess.htm
Rickards, M. (2000). The encyclopedia of ephemera: A guide to the fragmentary documents of everyday life for the collector, curator, and historian. New York: Routledge.
Rosenberry, M. C. (1944, April). The army music program. Music Educators Journal, 30(5), 18-19, 48-49. Retrieved from JSTOR.
Ruby, J. (1995). Secure the shadow: Death and photography in America. London: The MIT Press.
Sherrow, V. (2006). Encyclopedia of hair: A cultural history. Westport, CT: Greenwood Press.
Simmons, J. (2011). A brief history of decals. In Everything About Ceramic Decals. Retrieved June 2, 2011, from http://www.ceramicdecals.org/History_of_Decals.html
Smithsonian Institution. (n.d.). Greetings from the Smithsonian: A postcard history of the Smithsonian Institution. In Smithsonian Institution Archives. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://siarchives.si.edu/history/exhibits/postcard/chronology.htm
Snodgrass, M. E. (2004). Encyclopedia of kitchen history. New York: Fitzroy Dearborn.
T&J Collectibles. (2009). A brief history of ink blotters. In eBay Reviews & Guides. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://reviews.ebay.com/A-Brief-History-of-Ink-Blotters_W0QQugidZ10000000010357920
The history of vintage luggage (2001, November 30). In News-Antique. Retrieved December 1, 2009, from http://news-antique.com/?id=781960&keys=luggage-leather-crocodile
Twede, D., & Selke, S. E. (2005). Cartons, crates, and corrugated board: Handbook of paper and wood packaging technology. Lancaster, PA: DEStech Publications, Inc.
Vintage and collectible blotters. (2011, May). In Pendemonium Vintage Writing Collectibles. Retrieved June 7, 2011, from http://www.pendemonium.com/blotters.htm
Wallace, R. (1953, December 21). Please remit [Electronic version]. Life, 42-52.
Cigarette cards; Ocean liners; International travel; House furnishings; Hotels.; Hatboxes; World War, 1914-1918.; Hardware; Hairstyles; Hairdressing; Hair dyes; Chewing gum; Greeting cards; Tonics (Medicinal preparations); Free material; Linoleum; Food -- United States.; Telegraph; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, American; Dry-goods -- United States.; Decoration and ornament -- Victorian style.; Agriculture; Household appliances; Advertising -- United States.; Agricultural machinery; Baking; Beauty, Personal; Beverages -- United States.; Cigarettes; Cigars; Clothing and dress -- United States.; Collecting of accounts -- United States.; Concessions (Amusements, etc.); Posters.; Cosmetics; Cruise lines; Patent medicines -- United States.; Patriotism; Patriotism in advertising; Penmanship; Pins and needles; Pinup art; Housekeeping; Popular music -- United States.; Leisure; Railroad travel; Rationing -- United States.; Sewing; Snack food industry; Theater -- United States.; Tobacco -- United States.; Tourism; Transportation -- United States.; Travel.; Advertisements.; Advertising blotters; Calendars.; Chromolithography.; Postmortem photography; Editorial cartoons.; Photographs.; Travel labels; Advertising cards.; Stickers; Stationery; Sheet music.; Ration books.; Propaganda.; Postcards.; Picture postcards.; Pamphlets.; Packaging; Needle cases; Military maps.; Magazines (periodicals).; Labels (identifying artifacts); Hairnets; Glassine; Ephemera.; Envelopes; Decals; Karp, Marilynn Gelfman, 1939-; Batchelor, Clarence Daniel, 1888-1977; United States. Army. Field Artillery; United States. Army. Signal Corps
- Series I. Greeting Cards, circa 1925-1945
  Historical note
  More than any other category of ephemera, greeting cards from past years survive in great numbers, often having been used in scrapbooks, or saved as personal mementos. The greeting card or "message of good will" as a personal form of communication has a long history, but emerged commercially during the 19th century, concurrent with the rise of a new and prosperous leisured middle class, the advent of reliable, efficient postal service, and new forms of mechanization in printing methods that made the mass production of color printing affordable for the first time. In America, the first leading exponent of the greeting card was German lithographer Louis Prang (1824-1909) who is credited as being the first to introduce chromolithography to the production of greeting cards in America. By the early 20th century, the foundations for a full-fledged industry had been laid with the founding of Hallmark (today, the world's largest greeting card company) in 1910. Throughout the 20th century, the variety of card themes and sentiments would evolve dramatically, from traditional annual celebrations to the acknowledgement of almost every experience in everyday life.
  - Birthday -- Specific Age, circa 1925-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birthday -- Specific Relationship, circa 1925-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Birthday -- General, circa 1925-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wedding/Engagement, circa 1925-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baby, circa 1925-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Confirmation, circa 1930s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Graduation/Commencement, circa 1920s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anniversary, circa 1925-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bon Voyage, circa 1925-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Please Write, circa 1920s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Get Well, circa 1925-1935 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thinking of You, 1926 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Holidays -- Christmas, circa 1915 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Holidays -- Easter, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Holidays -- Valentine, circa 1920s-1940s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - World War II, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II. Postcards, circa 1906-1955
  In the United States, the first mailable postcards appeared in 1873. These early "Postal Mailing Cards" were pre-stamped and government issued, until the Private Mailing Card Act of 1898 allowed for the independent production of postcards (called "Private Mailing Cards" until 1901, when the government first permitted privately-issued postcards to use the words "Post Card" on their reverse side). Until 1907, postcards had no "divided backs," as all messages for the addressee were allowed only on the face of the card--often in a designated message box. The advent of Chicago's World's Columbian Exposition in 1893, contributed to the immense popularity of "view cards" (or "picture postcards"), which sparked a postcard-collecting craze throughout the country, reaching its zenith in 1915. Following World War I, the postcard industry (previously dominated by German production) flourished in the United States, with millions of postcards produced, mailed, and collected annually. Today, postcards from the past continue to fascinate us, offering a compelling window into topographical and social history.
  Arrangement note
  The postcards in this series have been arranged thematically with subject titles assigned by the collector. Place Banner postcards are arranged alphabetically by city.
  - American Patriotism -- General, circa 1910-1976 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Patriotism -- American Flag Incantations, before 1920 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17a)
  - American Patriotism -- World War I, circa 1914-1918 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - American Patriotism -- World War II, circa 1940-1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Humor -- World War II, circa 1940-1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Humor -- 1940's Girlie, circa 1940s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Multiple Choice, circa 1930-1945 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Victorian Sentiments, circa 1907-1915 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Victorian Sentiments, circa 1907-1915 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Victorian Sentiments, circa 1907-1915 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - Victorian Sentiments, circa 1907-1915 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Victorian Sentiments, circa 1907-1915 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Trolleys, circa 1913-1977 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Trains, 1904-circa 1970s, bulk after 1960 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 29)
  - Trains, circa 1907-1980s, bulk after 1960 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Trains, circa 1960s-1980s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - Stations and Waiting Rooms, circa 1910-1950, bulk 1940s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Planes and Ships, circa 1910s-1950s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - Place Banners (U.S. Cities), A-E, circa 1910s-1940s, bulk 1910s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
  - Place Banners (U.S. Cities), E-M, circa 1910-1920 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
  - Place Banners (U.S. Cities), M-P, circa 1910s (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
  - Place Banners (U.S. Cities), S-Z, circa 1910s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
  - Birthday, circa 1910's-1940's (Offsite-box 18, Folder 204)
  - Holidays (New Years and Valentine's Day), circa 1900's - 1920's (Offsite-box 18, Folder 205)
  - Names, circa 1900's (Offsite-box 18, Folder 206)
  - Foldout, circa 1910's - 1920's (Offsite-box 18, Folder 207)
  - General, circa 1900's (Offsite-box 18, Folder 208)
- Series III. Trade and Trading Cards, circa 1875-1915, 1964
  Condition note
  Many of the trade cards have been glued/pasted to their plastic sleeve; trade card sleeves need to be evaluated to see if they are archivally safe.
  While the concept of advertising "trade cards" dates back to the 1700s, it was not until the latter part of the 19th century that the development of trade cards gained great popularity in the United States, due in large part to advancements in affordable color printing (chromolithography). In the 1870s, the lithographer and printer Louis Prang was influential in popularizing the idea of cheaply mass-producing such cards for the needs of the advertising trade. Sometimes inserted into packages, they served as an effective means of advertising goods and services (similar to today's business cards), and had the additional appeal of offering the consumer a collectable giveaway item. Trade cards were often produced in a numbered series of related images (such as the Sollers & Co. full set in this collection) that could be incorporated into artistic crafts and scrapbooks. By the beginning of the 20th century, the production of trade cards fell into gradual disuse with the increasing prevalence of advertising in magazines and newspapers.
  This series also includes a complete set of John F. Kennedy trading cards, issued by Topps in 1964. The set includes 77 cards with a large black and white photo on the front and a short caption describing the image on the back. Images depict Kennedy as President and as family man, relaxing with his wife Jackie and kids Caroline and John.
  This series of trade cards was received from the collector in three-ring binders and later disbound and rehoused. Both the collector's category titles and order of binder contents have been maintained in the series list below.
  - Cures, circa 1875-1910 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
  - Druggists, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
  - Vaccines, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
  - Publishers, Stationers, and Schools, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
  - Political, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41)
  - Tobacco, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 42)
  - Gum, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 43)
  - Insurance, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 44)
  - Soap, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 45)
  - Laundry Products (includes starches and dye), circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 46)
    See Also
    Laundry Products
  - Hair Dyes and Restorers, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 47)
  - Colognes, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 48)
  - Cosmetics, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 49)
  - Foods, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 50)
  - Clothiers / Dry Goods, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 51)
  - Shoes, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 52)
  - Threads, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 53)
  - Various (includes 2 items of theater-related ephemera), circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 54)
  - Farm Machinery, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 55)
  - Fertilizers (includes seeds and nurseries), circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 56)
  - Sewing Machines, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 57)
  - Steamship Lines (includes steamboats), circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 58)
  - Stoves, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 59)
  - Cleaners, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 60)
  - Hardware, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 61)
  - Oil/Glue, circa 1875-1910 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 62)
  - Furniture (includes pianos and organs), circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 63)
  - Various (includes brick presses, sifters, pumps & fire engines, shotgun powder, vehicles), circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 64)
  - Sollers & Co. Trade Cards (full set), circa 1880 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 65)
  - Redeemable Baking Soda Trade Cards, circa 1875-1915 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 66)
    Historical Note